Miguel Xochicale

School of Biomedical Engineering and Imaging Sciences Department of Surgical and Interventional Engineering King's College London, UK

■ miguel.xochicale@kcl.ac.uk

↑ http://mxochicale.github.io/ · □ mxochicale

Research Interests My research interests are in the creation of Signal and Image Processing techniques in the context of Human-Robot Interaction, Wearables in Medicine, Ultrasound-Guided Interventions, Medical Robotics, and Research Software Engineering.

EDUCATION

The University of Birmingham

Birmingham, UK

Ph.D. in Computer Engineering

Nov 2014 - Nov 2018

Thesis: Nonlinear Analysis to Quantify Movement Variability in Human-Humanoid Interaction.

Supervisors: Professor Chris Baber and Professor Martin Russell

Thesis submission: 26/10/2018. Passed Viva: 11/01/2019. Awarded PhD degree: 12/07/2019.

Links: Thesis: 🗗 Github: 🐱 Website: 🗹

Institute of Astrophysics, Optics and Electronics (INAOE)

Puebla, México

M.Sc. in Signal Processing

Sep 2004 - Sep 2006

Thesis: Design of digital filters with fewer multipliers

Supervisor: Dr. Gordana Jovanovic Dolecek

Links: Thesis: 译Github: 🖶

Puebla Institute of Technology

Puebla, México

Aug 1999 – Sep 2004

B.Eng. in Electronics Thesis: Speed control for a two-degrees-of-freedom Robot in LabVIEW.

Supervisor: M.Sc. José Esteban Torres León.

Links: Thesis: 🖾 Github: 🐱

Professional Experience

King's College London Research Associate in Software and Hardware Engineering London UK

Apr 2019 – Present

- PI: Prof. Tom Vercauteren
- I am pushing forward the state-of-the-art of Ultrasound-Guidance Interventions where am involved in the development of a needle tip tracking system, real-time ultrasound image processing, quality management system (QMS) and clinical translation of medical devices, and public engagement activities. Similarly, I am developing validation experiments with linear stages under Windows and GNU/Linux OSs, designing electronic PCBs and 3D printing holders, characterising ultrasonic transducers, and contributing to a Python library via GitHub. All the previous activities in collaboration with an amazing team of renowned clinicians, engineers, QMS specialists and researchers in KCL and UCL. Additionally, I am leading the preparation of two manuscripts. See more at ().

INAOE's Robotics Laboratory Research Assistant in Robotics

Puebla, México Feb 2013 – Aug 2013

- Advisor: Dr. Angélica Muñoz Meléndez
- I developed a Human-Robot Interaction application for dancing activities based on a Patrolbot mobile robot and a single three-axial accelerometer. (See documents and code: 🗹).

Madero University Teaching Lecturer in Mechatronic Engineering

Puebla, México Jan 2012 – Jan 2013

• I proposed and supervised the following students projects: Haptic Referee Glove, Lightmetre and Pychometre Sensors, Smart Irrigation, Persistent Of Vision Bicycle Wheel and a Delta Robot Structure (See documents and code: 🗷).

• I proposed and designed a Mechatronic Laboratory which includes: (i) a benchmark for laboratories in mechatronics in México and Puebla, (ii) a 3D layout design and (iii) minimal requirements of hardware and software for the laboratory (See documents and layout: 2.).

INAOE Research Internship in Robotics

Puebla, México

Sep 2003 - Mar 2004

• I implemented a speed control for a two-degree-of-freedom robot with microcontrollers PIC 16F84 & 16F877 which communicated via RS-232 to LabVIEW's Virtual Instruments.

TEACHING AND Supervision EXPERIENCE

King's College London **Teaching Associate**

London, UK

Ian 2020 - Present

• Medical Robotics. Lecturer: Dr. Hongbin Liu

Jan 2021 - Apr 2021 Jan 2020 - Apr 2020

• Medical Robotics. Lecturer: Dr. Christos Bergeles Supervision

Jan 2020 – Present

Student: Alexander Mitton

Jan 2020 - Sep 2020

M.Sc. Project: Vibro-tactile stimulator for dystonia research Co-supervisors: C. Bergeles, V. Mcclelland and A. Worley

The University of Birmingham **Teaching Associate**

Birmingham, UK Aug 2014 – Apr 2018

• Engineering Maths 2. Lecturers: Professor Martin Russell, Dr Carl Anthony Jan 2018 – Apr 2018 Aug 2017 - Dec 2017 • Engineering Maths 2. Lecturer: Professor Martin Russell • Computing for Engineering. Lecturer: Dr Sridhar Pammu Aug 2017 - Dec 2017 • Matlab Laboratories. Lecturer: Dr Edward Tarte Jan 2017 - Apr 2017 • Computing for Engineering. Lecturer: Dr Sridhar Pammu Aug 2016 - Dec 2016 • Small Embedded Systems. Lecturer: Professor Chris Baber

Jun 2018 - Dec 2018 Supervision

Student: Dinghuang Zhang

M.Sc. Project: Tools for Human-Humanoid Collaboration

Co-supervisor: Chris Baber.

Bilingual Hight School TECMilenio University **Teaching Associate**

Puebla, México

Aug 2016 - Dec 2016

Aug 2013 - Dec 2013

• Information Technology 🗷, Euclidean Geometry 🖸, and Microsoft Office Access 🖸

Universidad Madero Teaching Associate in Mechatronic Eng.

Puebla, México

Ian 2012 - Dec 2012

• Fundamentals of Automation 🗹, Industrial Electronics 🖸, Research Projects 🖸, Metrology 🖸, Physics **7**, and Computer Integrating Manufacturing, and Power Electronics

Universidad Iberoamericana Puebla Teaching Associate in Electronic Eng.

Puebla, México

Ian 2007 - Dec 2011

• Stochastic Processes 🗷, Digital Signal Processing 🗹, and Analog Filters.

Instituto Tecnológico Superior de Atlixco Teaching Associate in Mechatronic Eng.

Puebla, México Aug 2006 - Jun 2007

- (01/2007 06/2007) Electronics I, Numerical Methods, and Electricity and Magnetism.
- (08/2006 12/2006) Electricity and Magnetism, and Electricity and Industrial Electronics

PUBLICATIONS

- 1. M. Xochicale and C. Baber, "Nonlinear methods to quantify movement variability in humanhumanoid interaction activities," Mar. 2021. arXiv: 1810.09249 [eess.SP], Full Manuscript.
- 2. R. Montenegro, E. Corona, D. Badillo-Perez, A. Mandujano, L. Vazquez, D. Cruz, and M. Xochicale, "Air4children: Artificial intelligence and robotics for children," in 16th Annual Conference on Human-Robot Interaction (HRI '21), Feb. 2021. arXiv: 2103.07637 [cs.R0].
- 3. M. Xochicale and C. Baber, "Towards the analysis of movement variability in human-humanoid imitation activities," in 5th International Conference on Human Agent Interaction (HAI '17), Bielefeld, Germany, Oct. 2017, Poster Paper.
- 4. M. Xochicale, C. Baber, and O. Mourad, "Towards the quantification of human-robot imitation using wearable inertial sensors," in 12th Annual Conference on Human-Robot Interaction (HRI '17), Vienna, Austria, Mar. 2017, Poster Paper.
- 5. M. Xochicale, C. Baber, and O. Mourad, "Analysis of the movement variability in dance activities using wearable sensors," in 2nd International Symposium on Wearable Robotics (WeRob '16), Segovia, Spain, Oct. 2016, Poster Paper.
- 6. M. Xochicale, C. Baber, and O. Mourad, "Understanding movement variability of simplistic gestures using an inertial sensor," in 5th ACM International Symposium on Pervasive Displays (PerDis '16), Oulu, Finland, Jun. 2016, Poster Paper.
- 7. M. Xochicale and G. Jovanovic-Dolecek, "A new method for design narrow band lowpass fir filters using a scale function," in 2nd International Conference on Electronic Design (ICED '06), Veracruz, Mexico, Nov. 2006, Conference Paper.

POSTERS

- 1. M. Xochicale, "Open-cortex: A continuous integration framework for open scientific communication," in 1st Conference on Reproducibility, Replicability and Trust in Science (RRTS '20), Cambridge, England (Virtual Conference), Sep. 2020, Poster Abstract.
- 2. M. Xochicale, "Quantification of dynamic facial expressions with shannon entropy in humanhumanoid interaction," in 1st Symposium on Machine Learning and Dynamical Systems (MLDS '19), London, UK, Feb. 2019, Poster Abstract.

TALKS

- 1. M. Xochicale and C. Baber, "Nonlinear analysis to quantify human movement variability from time-series data," in neuromatch 3.0 (NMC3 '20), Virtual Conference, Oct. 2020, Presentation
- 2. M. Xochicale, "Quantifying movement variability with nonlinear dynamics for human-humanoid interaction," in 25th International Conference on Difference Equations and Applications (ICDEA '19), London, UK, Jun. 2019, Slices abstract.
- 3. M. Xochicale, "Quantifying the inherent chaos of human movement variability," in 15th Experimental Chaos and Complexity Conference (ECCC '18), Madrid, Spain, Jun. 2018, Presentation Abstract.
- 4. M. Xochicale and C. Baber, "Towards the analysis of movement variability for facial expressions with nonlinear dynamics," in 7th Consortium of European Research on Emotion Conference (CERE '18), Glasgow, Scotland, UK, Apr. 2018, Presentation abstract.

AND HONOURS

- GRANTS, AWARDS King's Public Engagement grant for the project "FETUS: Finding a fETus with an Ultrasound Simulator" led by myself and in collaboration with Fang-Yu Lin and Shu Wang 🗹 (07/01/2021 -07/01/2022)
 - Alexander Mitton won the Outstanding Individual Project award for his M.Sc. project, which I was the main supervisor, on designing a wearable, vibrotactile stimulation device for patients with dystonia 🗹 (15/10/2020)
 - King's Health Partners grant for the project "Sensory system abnormalities in childhood dystonia" lead by Verity McClelland and in collaboration with Carlos Seneci (14/04/2020 -9/06/2020)
 - My work "Towards Healthy Ageing with Humanoid Robots" was selected for a talk at the second forum of Mexican Talent, Innovation Match MX 2017, 🗹 🔁 🛗 11/01/2017
 - I won the best poster award at the XIV Symposium of Mexican Students in the UK at University of Edinburgh 🗹 16-18/06/2016
 - My project of a low-cost robot was selected among 125 applications received from 35 countries and presented at the first international public entrepreneurship program in Mexico (MECATE 2015). 🗹 🛗 20-24/07/2015
 - Ph.D. scholarship by the Mexican National Council on Science and Technology. 11/2014-11/2018

- Markovito's team won the first place at the Mexican Tournament of Robotics 2013 in the category at HOME where I presented a Human-Robot Interaction Dance Demo. 25-27/05/2013
- M.Sc. scholarship by the Mexican National Council on Science and Technology. 09/2004-09/2006

SKILLS

Programming Python[2014-present], R[2013-present], Robot Operating System (ROS)[2016present], GNU-Octave (or MatLab)[2009-present], LATEX[2006-present], C and C++[2015present], Processing[2012-present], the shell[2010-present], GNU-emacs[2010-present], vim[2016present], pandoc[2017-present], open-source enthusiast at GitHub (@mxochicale)[2015-present], and continuous integration and continuous delivery [2019-present].

Tools GNU/Linux Operating System user (e.g. OpenSuse, Debian and Ubuntu)[2005-present] Single-board computers and microcontrollers (e.g. NVIDIA Jetson Nano, RaspberryPi, Beagle-Bone, Arduino and PIC)[2010-present], Inertial Measurement Units (e.g. calibration, collection and data analysis)[2013-present], Web design (e.g. Github pages, Jekyll)[2015-present], and Graphic design (e.g. Inkscape, GIMP)[2014-present], CAD design (e.g. Autodesk invetor, blender, FreeCAD)[2015-present], Artificial Neural Networks (e.g. TensorFlow and PyTorch)[2017-present], and 3D printing (e.g., flsun, cura) [2019-present].

Languages Spanish[Native], English[Fluent], Chinese[Beginner]

EXTRA ACTIVITIES

King's College London Outreach activities and scientific engagement

aged 14-18 to STEAM ♥

London, UK Sep 2019 - Present

- Participant in the STEAM WEEK organised by the City Westminster Council to engage students 23-03-2021
- · Alexandra Lautarescu and I organised the Reproducible, Interpretable, Open, & Transparent Science Club at St Thomas' Hospital 02-2020 - 06-2020
- For the event In2ScienceUK, I shared my scientific journey to young scientist on how they can become better scientist. 20-08-2019
- For the New Scientist Live, I showcased software segmentation that helps doctors to create 3D 09-2019 models of brain tumors using AI.

University of Birmingham Outreach activities and scientific engagement

Birmingham, UK Aug 2014 - Jun 2018

- Finalist at the Three Minute Thesis Competition 2018. Video: 🛗 and GitHub: 🖶 05-2018
- Research Poster Conference for (2015) [2], (2016) [2], and (2018) [2]. GitHub: [3].
- Demoing Human-Robot Activities at the Undergraduate Open Days. GitHub: 5. 2014–2018
- Coordinator of the Science Seminars for the Mexican Society. GitHub: , Website: . 2017– 2018

FREE AIR4Children México & UK

- Building Artificial Intelligence and Robotics for Children (air4children) with the purpose of teaching AIR to children for free. Twitter: **y**@air4children GitHub: **™**@air4children Present
- Creation Libre Robotics, a non-profit organization aiming to freely transfer knowledge in Robotics to Mexican children. Website: 2013 - 2017

Developer of the Website "Machine Learning for México"

México & UK 2013 - 2018

• GitHub: 🖪, Website: 🖸